I have one sutor here and a few
questions is paying attention to
Pleasant breathing Sensations a valid
practice for developing of the Right
View no absolutely
not and it
seems that that kind of practice to pay
attention to Pleasant breathing
Sensations seems to be just another sensual
seems to be just another sensual
act I know it's not the same as SE a
sexual act but it's still a pleasant
physical act that one can absorb into
and therefore try to escape suffering
through pleasure which is the point of
any sensual act it is it is um any
Sensations basically is just another
word for
tactile so it means it's it's a TCT
sense that comes on the base of your
body and even if it's not necessarily
Pleasant if your practice is just to
attend to the sensations of the tactile
nature which is the nature of Sensations
there are no Sensations that are not
tactile people often tend to uh assume
Sensations are like V and feelings but
they're not they're completely tactile
like sensation of of uh things touching
your skin or Sensations on the inside of
your body that you can have a tactile
sensor of so observing Sensations it's
always going to be on the level of
perception so Sensations can never be
feelings because as the sutas say what
is feeling well feeling is that which
feels and what is perception perception
is that which perceives so perception
perceives feeling feels but people kind
of through that kind of mess of of their
own understanding and
information while they're perceiving a
mere tactile Sensations they think
they're being ful of V of feeling which
is always completely the opposite
direction of where you where your
attention is um so in expecting that the
Right View would come on a kind of close
watching of tactile Sensations you can
see how how how mistaken that is on so
many levels it implies the truth comes
from just magical appearance through
your senses like beyond your senses and
that presents itself through through
some some uh practice of
observation but that's not understanding
that's just witnessing a random thing
that then you believe to be your
Enlightenment or or soap partti or
whatever else but if you read the suas
there's no mention of that
whatsoever it starts with a gradual
training withdrawal from un wholesome
and then
Discerning skillful is skillful and
unskillful is unskillful recognizing the
root of the UNH wholesome Discerning it
fully understanding it not not feeding
it through your ignorant actions and
wrong attention and that's how you undo
the entire
samsara through that diligent work of
abstaining from things that should be
abstained and cultivating things that
should be
cultivated and you could see how the
modern practice of sensation watching as
I often said it's like like staring at
the as often said it's like it's like
staring at the basically trying to
trying to hunt down the moment where the
truth will just magically reveal itself
and you could see how how that idea
would be
popular because kind of does away with
all the tedious part of pain and
development that you have to go through
as with anything that new that you're
learning and picking up a craft in a
skill and understanding so all I need to
do is just get closer and closer and
closer to my sensation watching to
observing the tactile things on the
basis of my body and then the truth will
just hit me and I'm just going to have a
magic experience um and then from then onwards
experience um and then from then onwards
everything will be
fine and it's like it's completely
circumstantial random and as I said it
does not exist in the sutas at
all at least not in the early sutas that
we talked
about the the later developments of
Buddhism they might have developed their
own scripture to support this certainly
commentaries invented this whole thing
starting from Buddha vuda and Abid dama
before that but that's not found in the
sutas the the path of purification how
they call it was very clear the gradual
training and he said
like if anybody the Buddha said if
anybody even in the past would have
attained Liberation or anything
approximating Liberation they would have
had to do it only through this way of
purifying virtue your actions in full
understanding of the the the the the
intentions which are the root of Kama
basically and if somebody claims that
they can develop uh full Enlightenment
purification apart from this such thing
is not possible so you ask yourself like
when you're watching your
Sensations what are you imply where what
what are you emphasizing what do you
what do you expect to
happen what do you expect to to to to to
to
occur and then see whether it aligns
with these ideas that you can broadly
find in the suas without any kind of
great effort of of insight and
understanding just through being
informed with the sutas you get a
general sense of what practice kind of
boils down to and then see is that what
you're expect is that what you're doing
is that what you're expecting to happen
when you're watching your Sensations and
committed to like concentrating harder
and harder and
harder I mean I often quoted that sutta
which was actually two sutas that I kind
of joined into one um where the Buddha
compared any such meditation to to um to
sensuality it says premeditate mism meditate over
it says premeditate mism meditate over
meditate under meditate basically when
you're wrongly attending to your
objects if you're expecting your
meditation your samadi to come out of
focusing on an
object it's already a form of meditation
with sensuality because you're
emphasizing the object of your senses
tactile and then in another suta the
mara uses the same wording of
premeditate mised Med itate over
meditate and then he adds the simulus to
illustrate that saying oh it's like a
jackal waiting down hunting down a mouse
waiting for it to appear to pounce on or
an owl of fish and and things like that
this is my novelty experience that this
must be you are expecting a novelty
experience to come and then when you oh
when you get it then that's a success
you caught it you hunted it down you got
it now but as I said that direction and
I'm not denying the reality of that by
the way the mouse the reality of novelty
experiences oh you can get loads what
I'm saying is that dama practice is
completely the opposite direction from
that so where your attention is when you
are focusing on your tactile Sensations
watching moment to moment moment to
moment expecting kapus to reveal the
truth to you and so on the Dharma the
understanding would be completely at the
back of that where you're not looking so
would you would you say that that mean
what you mean there is
you need to be able to understand the
nature of experience you need to be able
to understand the nature of your
intentions which begins through
purifying your bodily
Behavior verbal behavior and mental
Behavior so you are responsible for your
thoughts which ones you welcome which
ones you cultivate which ones you allow
to to sort of linger around and which
ones you ignore but most people don't
even see that they might be able to take
on the precepts keep keep the keep the
physical restraint maybe police their
speech a bit better and so on but
mentally they're just subjected to what
their mind thinks and then they just try
to to get rid of it get rid of these
thoughts but either way they don't see
that they are actually responsible for
them so that's the gradual training that
then once your behavior and virtue has
been established you get to notice kind
of the same pattern if you're looking at
things rightly uh you have to notice the
same pattern regarding your thoughts
which is the pattern of oh so there is a
thought Arisen I haven't created it the
possibility presented itself to do this
or to not do that which one do I relish
which one do I emphasize which one do I
lean towards which one do I cultivate
which one do I
welcome so I remove the welcoming I said
no I should not welcome that but I don't
try to get rid of it I don't try to deny
it I don't try to focus away and pretend
it's not there I basically take
responsibility for the pressure that
that thought exerts on me without trying
to destroy the thought CU that would be
already overstepping into Mar's
domain so if I just go to another
question um can I not use such a practice of
um can I not use such a practice of
focusing on Pleasant breathing to
replace my co sensual acts if I find joy
in simple attention to the breath I hope
that my mind will want that pleasure
instead of other dangerous Pleasures I
hope to find a pleasure which is
separate from sensuality so that I can
experience the joy of J so that's that's
the yeah that's the idea that's the
basic idea it is see the problem with
that idea is that person whoever asked
that they admit that focusing on the
central pleasure of the breath is better
than core sensuality but what they don't
understand is that the danger
of course
sensuality is still present in the
danger of your sensual
breath because the danger uh the danger
of sensual desire is not because they're
coarse or subtle it's because they
pertain to the body it's because they're
tactile because they're physical the
senses are Mara's domain so
fundamentally what you would be doing in
such practice is replacing one thing
within Mara's domain with the subtler
thing within Mara's domain and thinking
you're avoiding the danger of the Mara's
domain while still remaining very much
within the same domain
unchanged that's why in
thata um can't remember maybe we can
quote it I don't remember the numbers um
it was basically what the Buddha said
that uh that one could enter and abide
develop the first Jan without having
already fully seen the gratification
danger escape in to sensuality and the
five hindrances in general such thing is
not possible so first you need to see that
possible so first you need to see that
danger pertaining to anything that you
would be attending for pleasure and
completely abandon that attitude then
and only then the pleasure of Jan can
arise when you don't look for it don't
need it don't seek it and that's why
that pleasure of Jana that's not being
sought in that Central manner is the
pleasure that's not underlined by the uh
under L Tendencies as the sutas would
say not in Mar's it's not in Mar's
domain so so from these
questions you know it seems like your
suffering you want to get rid of well
free from suffering get rid of suffering
your You Want To Get Right
View so instead of doing all these
coarse UNH wholesome actions sexual
actions you you go into these subtle
actions of you know doesn't hurt
anyone you know in a CO manner might be
the wrong View and so
on but it's still the same I want
pleasure to get pleasure yeah because
I'm suffering yeah and pleasure is the
freedom it's going to be it's inevitable
that a person will be doing it to some
extent in other words if you are
withdrawn from UNH wholesome things the
course UNH wholesome things say you
celebrate keeping the precepts and so on
you will be finding you know sensual
semi sensual joy in other things on your
day-to-day basis like going for a walk
uh doing this or doing that it's not
always but it could be sensual in that
sense but that's not the main issue
that's that if you if you continue with
the purification of behavior if you
don't revert back to the course uh UNH
wholesome uh clearly UNH wholesome
Pleasures this will kind of level itself
out the issue is if you were to think
that for example the pleasure of a of a
of a nice walk in the nature peaceful
beautiful sounds birds chirping if you
were to hold the view that that is your
Jana is the practice of Dharma is is
getting rid of of the sensuality that's
really the problem so see if a person is
watching their breath as I said many
times to to calm down cuz they were
agitated or whatever else but without
implying with their view with their
emphasis that this is the practice of
samadi and and and Jana and Right View
there would be no problem
really because this will lead me to
exactly it's the implication behind that
action which is that oh this is the
practice that takes me away from
sensuality which it doesn't into into
the Right View they will then magically
happen through the novelty pleasure that
will arise on account of this refined
sensuality and it's like oh that's the
problem it's your view there but if you
don't have that view and then you watch
your breath CU you're bored of something
fine it's not going to take you too far
out it's not going to sort of corrupt
you but you realize most often more
often than not when people ask these
questions they don't ask them mutually
they don't ask them in this sense they
ask them is is this a valid practice for
enlightenment for uprooting of
sensuality for becoming anagami and as I
said it's a categorical no